

HUGO CUI







PROFILE

LANGUAGES

French Native

CFFR B2

Spanish CEFR B1 I am an independent postdoc fellow in applied mathematics in the Center of Mathematical Sciences and Applications (CMSA) at Harvard University. Prior to that, I did my PhD studies in Physics at EPFL, advised by Lenka Zdeborová. My research lies at the crossroads of statistical physics, machine learning theory and high-dimensional probability, and aims at reaching a theoretical understanding of learning in neural networks.

EDUCATION



Harvard

2024-

Cambridge, USA

Postdoctoral fellow in applied mathematics, at the Center for Mathematical Sciences and Applications (Harvard CMSA).



EPFL

2020-2024

Lausanne. Switzerland

PhD candidate in machine learning theory and physics, SPOC laboratory at EPFL, advised by Lenka Zdeborová.



ENS Paris

2016-2020

Paris, France

- 2019: MSc in theoretical physics (ICFP), Highest Honours
- 2017: Bachelor in physics, Highest Honours
- 2016: Entrance via national competitive exam, rank 1/1000+

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE



Courant Institute, NYU

2023

New York, USA

PhD visiting student, hosted by Eric Vanden-Eijnden.



Capital Fund Management

2020

Paris, France

Risk dept. intern.



Institute of Theoretical Physics

2019-2020

Paris, France

Master thesis at IPhT (CEA Saclay) supervised by Lenka Zdeborová.



University of Zurich

2018

Zurich, Switzerland

Research internship, Theoretical condensed matter lab, with Titus Neupert.

NON-PROFIT



Innovation Forum

2020-2021

Lausanne. Switzerland

Business associate at the Swiss branch. Promotion of start-ups and technological transfer through interviews, conferences. Organisation of an accelerator and mentorship program for early stage start-ups.



CERTIFICATIONS



Cambridge Proficiency Certificate CEFR C2



Chinese Proficiency Evaluation HSK 5



Swiss Innovation Agency Business Concepts Certificate

AWARDS

- 2024: G-Research PhD prize in mathematics and data science, EPFL 3rd
- 2024: Recipient of a competitive Harvard CMSA Postdoctoral Fellowship
- 2021: Famelab (international science communication competition) finalist, representing Switzerland.
- 2021: Famelab Switzerland national winner
- 2016: Ranked 1st /1000+ at Ecole Normale Supérieure national entrance exam
- 2016: Ranked 4th/1000+ at French Ecole Polytechnique national entrance exam
- 2014: Bronze medal at 46th International Chemistry Olympiads
- 2014: 2nd prize at French National Chemistry Olympiads
- 2014: Laureate of two of the French Academy of Science thematic awards
- 2014: 2nd prize at French National Physics & Chemistry Concours Général

PUBLICATION LIST

- · High-dimensional learning of narrow neural networks, H. Cui, preprint arXiv:240913904
- A phase transition between positional and semantic learning in a solvable model of dot-product attention, H. Cui, F. Behrens, F. Krzakala, L. Zdeborová, NeurIPS 2024 Spotlight (top 3.6% of submissions).
- <u>Asymptotics of feature learning in two-layer networks after one gradient-step.</u> H. Cui, L. Pesce, Y. Dandi, F. Krzakala, Y. M. Lu, L. Zdeborová, B. Loureiro, ICML 2024 *Spotlight* (top 3.5% of submissions).
- · Asymptotics of learning with deep structured (random) features, D.Schröder, D.Dmitriev, H.Cui, B.Loureiro, ICML 2024.
- Analysis of learning a flow-based generative model from limited sample complexity, H. Cui, E. Vanden-Eijnden, F. Krzakala, L. Zdeborová, ICLR 2024
- <u>High-dimensional asymptotics of denoising auto-encoders</u>, H. Cui, L. Zdeborová, NeurIPS 2023 Spotlight (top 3.6% of submissions).; invited to the J. Stat. Mech 2024 machine learning special issue.
- <u>Bayes-Optimal Learning of Deep Random Networks of Extensive Width</u>, **H. Cui**, F. Krzakala, L. Zdeborová, ICML 2023 *Oral* (top 2.4% of submissions); invited to the J. Stat. Mech 2024 machine learning special issue.
- <u>Deterministic Equivalent and Error Universality of Deep Random Features</u>, D.Schröder*, **H.Cui***, D.Dmitriev, B.Loureiro, ICML 2023; invited to the J. Stat. Mech 2024 machine learning special issue.
- Error Rates for Kernel Classification under Source and Capacity conditions, H. Cui, B. Loureiro, F. Krzakala, L. Zdeborová, MLST 2023
- Large deviations in Semi-Supervised Learning in the Stochastic Block Model, H. Cui, L. Saglietti, L. Zdeborová, Phy, Rev. E 2022
- Generalization Error rates for Kernel Ridge Regression: the Crossover from the Noiseless to the Noisy Regime, H. Cui, B. Loureiro, F. Krzakala,
 L. Zdeborová, NeurIPS 2021; invited to the J. Stat. Mech 2022 machine learning special issue.
- Large deviations in the perceptron model and consequences for active learning, H. Cui, L. Saglietti, L. Zdeborová, MSML 2020 and MLST 2021
- <u>Capturing the learning curves of generic features maps for realistic data sets with a teacher-student model</u>, B. Loureiro, C. Gerbelot, H. Cui, S. Goldt, F. Krzakala, M. Mézard, L. Zdeborová, NeurlPS 2021; invited to the J. Stat. Mech 2022 machine learning special issue.

